Minnie S. Woodson Family Genealogical Collection 091
DCPL Special Collections - MLK Library
Minnie S. Woodson Family Genealogical Collection
1842-1994
DCPL Special Collections - MLK Library
Woodson, Minnie Shumate, 1921-1994
091
1 Linear feet
2 Boxes
Arrangement
Processed without series. The folders are arranged alphabetically by topic.
Biographical / Historical
For many years, the Woodson family has contended that their relative, Thomas Woodson, was the oldest son of President Thomas Jefferson and Sally Hemings. Oral tradition and correspondence lent credence to this claim and helped bring it to the attention of the administrators of Jefferson's estate, Monticello. Although DNA tests were inconclusive, after much research and discussion, Thomas Woodson was added as a potential child of Jefferson. This was due, in part, to Minnie Shumate Woodson's research and writings. After graduating from Dunbar High School in 1937, Woodson went on to attend Miner's Teacher College and George Washington University. She later worked as an elementary school teacher and served as the president of the Washington, D.C. School Board. Minnie became part of the Woodson family when she married John Stanton Woodson, son of noted civil engineer Howard Woodson (the namesake of Woodson High School). She became intrigued by the family stories about Thomas Woodson and Thomas Jefferson. She began research into the family's history and eventually published two works: The Sable Curtain and The Woodson Family Source Book.
Custodial History
John Woodson donated the collection of his wife's research materials to the DC Public Library in July 1994.
Related Materials
Collection 093, H. D. Woodson and Metropolitan A. M. E. Church Collection.
Scope and Contents
This collection consists of materials collected by Minnie S. Woodson while researching the history of the Woodson family, including items such as clippings, census records, family trees, articles, photographs, correspondence, and newsletters. Of particular interest is information regarding the Afro-American Historical and Genealogical Society newsletter.
Genealogy; African Americans; Photographs; Newsletters; Correspondence; Families
- Series 1
  - Afro-American Historical and Genealogical Society - Book Order Forms, 1982-1986 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Afro-American Historical and Genealogical Society - Journal, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Afro-American Historical and Genealogical Society - Newsletter, 1978-1986 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Afro-American Historical and Genealogical Society - Newsletter Notes, 1980-1986 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Afro-American Historical and Genealogical Society - Programs, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Brodie, 1974-1980 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Callaloo (Poetry about Ally Hemmings), 1983 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Clewell Family, Undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Clippings, 1980-1991 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Reverend John Lewis Cohorn, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence, 1944-1985 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Family Tree - Jefferson Family, Undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Family Tree - Woodson, Undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Family Tree - Woodson - Smith Branch, Undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Famous Black Americans (autographed), 1975 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - "The Fort Robinson YMCA, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Goochland County - Virginia, Undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Greenbriar Family Line, Undated (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Lewis A. Leach, 1934 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Library of Congress - Searching the Local History and Genealogy Room, Undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - List of Free Black Heads of Families in the First Census, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - New Images - Newsletter, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Officer's Clubs, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Pennsylvania Abolition Society Guide, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Personal Property Tax Studies, Undated (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Record of Black and Mulatto Persons in Jackson County - Ohio, 1961 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Carter G. Woodson, Undated (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Woodson Family - Alabama, Undated (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Woodson Family - Article, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Woodson Family - Article, 1994 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Woodson Family - Cumberland County, Undated (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Woodson Family - Frances Line, Undated (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Woodson Family - Highgate Branch – Canada, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Woodson Family - Jemima Line, Undated (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Woodson Family - Lewis Line (with photographs), 1842-1980 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Woodson Family - Link to Thomas Jefferson, 1991-1992 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Woodson Family - Newsletter, 1987-1991 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Woodson Family - Photographs (copies, Undated (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Woodson Family - Source Book - Bills, 1982 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Granville Lewis Woodson (with photograph), 1974 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Minnie S. Woodson - Obituary, 1994 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Minnie S. Woodson - Oral History, Undated (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Minnie S. Woodson - The Sable Curtain - Outline, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Minnie S. Woodson - The Sable Curtain - Research, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Thomas Wesley Woodson, 1916 (Box 2, Folder 29)